Adam Tolley Web Application Architect

Web Platform Practitioner

My career comprises over a decade of modern web development with HTML, css, and javascript.

As web development has evolved from statically served pages, to client-heavy SPAs, to full-stack hybrid client/server applications I have continuously broadened and deepened my skill set.

A problem solver first, my best work has been in creating solutions that boost developer effectiveness, code reusability, and cross department collaboration.

Skills and Experience Across the Entire Stack

- next.js, react, web components, lit, stencil.js, 11ty, astro
- javascript, typescript, c#, python, shell scripting, functional programming
- SQL, GraphQL, REST APIs, sanity.io, contentful, headless cms
- html, css, scss, svg, styled components, emotion, css-in-js, vanilla extract.
- JAM stack, SSR, SSG, island architecture, SPA, PWA, MVC, MV VM, MV*
- AWS, lambda, microservices, ec2, elastic beanstalk, amplify, cognito
- git, SCM, agile methodologies, code review, scrum, best practices, mentorship
- unit testing, integration testing, jest, mocha, TDD, automation, puppeteer, playwright
- naming things, cache invalidation

Recent Accomplishments

- Championed greater collaboration between Design and Development teams at by establishing common practices, terminology and workflows between departments
- Designed and lead development of our in-house hybrid SSG/SSR JAM stack web metaframework which:
 - Enables familiar page-building paradigms within a more flexible structured content CMS (sanity.io)
 - Augments common CSS-in-JS frameworks with a set of composable utility functions
 - Maps deeply nested backend data to explicit TypeScript objects, using recursive type generics
- Built react/redux tooling for dynamic data-driven construction of complex web forms and business logic

Employment History

HZ Design Group	Principal Architect	Apr 2022 - May 2023
HZ Design Group	Senior Software Engineer	Feb 2020 - Apr 2022
Frederick Mutual Insurance	Senior Software Engineer	May 2019 - Jan 2020
Social Security Administration	Developer (contract)	Jan 2019 - May 2019
DivvyCloud	Senior Software Engineer (contract)	Apr 2018 - Oct 2018
Washington Post	Senior Software Engineer (contract)	Jan 2017 - Jan 2018
Independent Contractor	Instructor and Consultant	Jan 2016 - Jan 2017
Decisive Communications	Senior Software Engineer	Mar 2015 - Jan 2016
NGP VAN	Software Engineer	Jan 2014 - Feb 2015
Marriott	Front End Developer (contract)	Feb 2013 - Dec 2013
Unison Inc	Front End Developer (contract)	Nov 2012 - Feb 2013

Education

- BS in Computer Science from Hood College in 2008
- AS in Computer Science from Frederick Community College in 2004
- Certificates: ScrumMaster (CSA) in 2013, MCSE, A+, and Net+ in 2000